<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The summe of Christian religion shewing the vndoubted truth holy practice, and heauenly comfort therein contained. With certaine necessary prayers. By Samuel Browne, preacher of Gods Word, at S. Maries in Shrewsbury.</title>
            <author>Browne, Samuel, 1575?-1632.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17038</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3911</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119313</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854520</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854520</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19946</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17038)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19946)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1196:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The summe of Christian religion shewing the vndoubted truth holy practice, and heauenly comfort therein contained. With certaine necessary prayers. By Samuel Browne, preacher of Gods Word, at S. Maries in Shrewsbury.</title>
                  <author>Browne, Samuel, 1575?-1632.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Badger, for Philemon Stephens and Christopher Meredith, and are to be sold at the golden Lyon in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first part is in question and answer format.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Catechisms --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19946:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19946:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SVMME OF CHRISTIAN RELIGION: Shewing the vndoubted Truth, <hi>holy Practice, and heauenly Comfort therein contained.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With certaine neceſſary PRAYERS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Browne,</hi> Preacher of Gods Word, at S. <hi>Maries</hi> in <hi>Shrewſbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. COR. 14. 3.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hee that prophecieth, ſpeaketh vnto men to edification, exhortation, and comfort.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Richard Badger,</hi> for <hi>Philemon Stephens</hi> and <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith,</hi> and are <hi>to be ſold at the golden Lyon in</hi> Pauls Church-yard, 1630.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:19946:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19946:2"/>
            <head>The Summe of Chriſtian RELIGION.</head>
            <div type="question">
               <head>Queſtion. <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Herein standeth a mans true hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi> In the recouery of Gods fauour by Chriſt, which we loſt by the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> our firſt parents.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What was their eſtate by creation?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They were created after the image of God, in wiſedome, holineſſe, and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 26. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 10. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 24. They enioyed the pleaſures of Paradiſe, and the plenty of the world, without any griefe of minde, or paine of body: They were free from death, ſo long as they were free from ſinne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How ſinned they?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:3"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> The diuell in the ſerpent entiſed the woman, and ſhe the man, to eat of the fruit forbidden vpon paine of death, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8. 44. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 3. 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Was the eating of that fruit a great and hainous ſinne?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yea, in many reſpects; for our parents beleeued not Gods threatning, and ſo made him a liar, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 10. They truſted not in his goodneſſe, but eſteemed him enuious, as one that withheld good things from them; but the deuill was beleeued, and eſteemed a kinde friend. They ſhewed deuilliſh pride, and vile ingratitude. They became rebels againſt their gracious God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What hurt receiue we by this their fall?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Hereby all mankinde is defiled with ſinne, originall and actuall, and therefore is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the wrath and curſe of God, <hi>Ro.</hi> 5. 12.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is originall ſinne?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſinne of <hi>Adam</hi> iuſtly imputed to vs all, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 19. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 10. together with the corruption of our nature thence enſuing. For by <hi>Adams</hi> fall, mans minde is darkened, his wil is become rebellious, his affections world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or brutiſh or deuilliſh, his conſcience hard or erroneous, and his whole nature infected,
<pb facs="tcp:19946:3"/> as it were with poiſon, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 5. 3. and 6. 5. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 17, 18.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How doth this appeare?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe euery natural man is void of the true knowledge of God, and of himſelfe, and of the way of true happineſſe. He is full of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, <hi>Ierem.</hi> 10. 14. 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 2. 14. He hath no power, nor true deſire to repent, to beleeue, or to obey, 2. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 3. 5. Hee is prone to al euill, vnapt to any good, vnder the power and ſtrong chaines of ſinne, and the bondage of the deuill, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 1, 2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 3.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is actuall ſinne?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The actuall tranſgreſſion of any of Gods Commandements, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 4.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What puniſhments are due to man for ſinne, originall and actuall?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. All corporall puniſhments, as war, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, peſtilence, and other diſeaſes, and all bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily torments, inflicted by God or man, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.</p>
               <p n="2">2. All ſpirituall puniſhments, as to be giuen ouer of God, to our owne blindneſſe and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, and to the ſeducement of the deuill and his inſtruments, <hi>Exod.</hi> 7. 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 24, 26. 2 <hi>Theſſalon.</hi> 2. 9, 10, 11.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Beſides theſe temporall puniſhments,
<pb facs="tcp:19946:4"/> the endleſſe and intolerable torments of hell, are the due deſert of our ſinnes, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 2. 17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 23. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 6.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How may we be deliuered from this hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible eſtate into which we are fallen, and recouer Gods fauour, and that bleſſed eſtate from whence we are fallen?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Gods loue and fauour may be recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, if being rightly prepared we come vnto him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. 28.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How may we be rightly prepared to come vnto Chriſt?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Gods Law contained in the Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, muſt be our Schoolemaſter; it will bring vs vnto Chriſt, if wee rightly vn-t<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtand it, and make vſe of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 20. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 19. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 24.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How may wee rightly vnderſtand theſe Commandements?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By obſeruing two things: Frſt, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Commandement doth command things good, and forbid things euill, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 14. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that euery commandement doth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid not only groſſe ſins, but alſo thoſe which the world accounteth ſmall ſinnes, or no ſins at all, <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 19. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 4. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 22. <hi>Iude v.</hi> 23.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:4"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How are the Commandements to bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Into two Tables: The firſt containing mans duty towards God; the ſecond his duty towards his neighbour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the firſt Commandement?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt haue none other Gods but me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is here commanded, and what forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This firſt Commandement containeth all inward duties of the heart towards God: As to know him, and chooſe him, to loue and to feare him aboue all, to truſt in him, to pray to him faithfully, to giue him thanks ſincerely <hi>Marke</hi> 12. 30. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 24. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 14, 15.</p>
               <p>Heere wee are not onely forbidden to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. 1. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 16. to haue the gods of the Heathen for our God, <hi>Ier.</hi> 2. 11, 12. or to ſeeke helpe and comfort from the deuill, by witchcraft ahd ſorcery, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19. 31. but the leaſt withdrawing of our hearts from God is here forbid, 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 22. 5. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 20. 13. <hi>Ier.</hi> 17. 5. and the ſetting of our hearts on riches, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and vaine-glory, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. 15, 16. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 5. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 4. all wandering thoughts at the time of prayer, preaching, and other holy exerciſes,
<pb facs="tcp:19946:5"/> 
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4. 17. <hi>Eſay</hi> 29. 13. <hi>Iam.</hi> 5. 16.</p>
               <p>Alſo to feare man more than God; as al they doe that commit thoſe ſinnes ſecretly, which they will not commit openly, <hi>Iob</hi> 24. 15. So euery paſſion of wicked griefe, or deſire, or ioy being againſt the loue of God, is againſt this Commandement, <hi>Matt.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 2. 10. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 27. 41. <hi>Iud.</hi> 18. 20. <hi>Luke.</hi> 22. 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Then belike they deceiue themſelues, that thinke this Commandement eaſie to bee kept, and that they can and doe keepe it.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Doubtleſſe they are greatly deceiued, for this Commandement is ofter broken than any other, and whichſoeuer Commandement a man breaketh, he breaketh this withall: for in euery ſinne a man erreth from that loue and feare which hee oweth to God, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19. 3, 4, 10, 12, 14, 16, 18, 24, 28, 30, 31, 32, 34, 36, 37.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the ſecond Commandement?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Here we are taught, how to worſhip God outwardly; that we doe it truly according to his word, and alſo diligently, and reuerently, <hi>Deu.</hi> 12. 32. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. 24. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 16, 17. <hi>Eccles:</hi> 4. 17.</p>
               <p>God here forbiddeth not only images, but all other falſe and ſuperſtitious worſhip, with
<pb facs="tcp:19946:5"/> all drowſineſſe, negligence, and all vnreuerent behauiour in his ſeruice, <hi>Math.</hi> 15. 9. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 48. 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the third Commandement?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt not take the Name, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Here we are commanded to talke often of Gods Maieſty, of his Word, and of his works, and that with all reuerence, and in our talke to defend truth and vertue, <hi>Deutero.</hi> 6. 6. Ezra. 8. 22.</p>
               <p>God here forbiddeth, not onely blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, profane ſwearing, and curſing, but alſo all fooliſh and idle talking of his Maieſty, and all profane maintayning of ſinne and error of his word, or of his workes, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 34. <hi>Iob</hi> 33. 8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>Iob</hi> 38. 2. and 39. 37, 38. <hi>Iob</hi> 42. 3. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 29. <hi>Col.</hi> 4. 6.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the fourth Commandement?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Remember that thou keepe holy, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>We are here commanded to beſtow Gods Sabbath in holy exerciſes, both publike and priuate; as in hearing, reading, praying, ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, meditating.</p>
               <p>God here forbiddeth, not only the labours of husbandry, handicrafts, and ſuch like, but alſo iournies on the Lords day, paying and alſo receiuing ſums of money, following of Law
<pb facs="tcp:19946:6"/> buſineſſe, making of bargaines, idleneſſe, and the choking of heauenly and ſpirituall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, by thoſe that on this day ſpecially, giue themſelues ouer to carnall pleaſures and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimes, <hi>Eſay</hi> 58. 13. <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 2. <hi>Reu.</hi> 1. 8. <hi>Neh.</hi> 13. 15.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the fruit of ſuch profaning of the Sabbath?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Barbarous and heatheniſh ignorance, and all manner of wickedneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the fifth Commandement?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Honour thy father and thy mother, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>By this Commandement, children, ſeruants, and all inferiours, muſt honour, that is, loue, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, and obey, their parents, maſters and other ſuperiours: And parents, &amp; maſters, are commanded to traine vp their children, and ſeruants, in godlineſſe; and Magiſtrates to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, Miniſters to inſtruct the people, as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full &amp; tender fathers. The contrary ſins, grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or leſſe, are here forbidden, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 22, <hi>&amp;c. Col.</hi> 3. 18, 19, 20. 21, 22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. 1. <hi>Pet</hi> 2. 13, 14. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 78. 71, 72. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13. 17. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 1, 2, 3.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the ſixt Commandement?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt doe no murther.</p>
               <p>We are here commanded, to performe all
<pb facs="tcp:19946:6"/> works of mercy towards our neighbour, both for body and ſoule, <hi>Eſay</hi> 58. 7. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 14. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 35.</p>
               <p>Not only killing, but alſo wounding, figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, quarrelling; al malice, all vnaduiſed anger, and all cruelty, in thought, word, or deed, are here forbidden, <hi>Matt.</hi> 5. 22. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 4, 5, 6. 1 <hi>Ioh</hi> 2. 11. and 3. 15.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the ſeuenth Commandement?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt not commit adultery.</p>
               <p>Here all chaſtity of body and minde is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, with a ſettled and conſtant reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, neuer to defile our ſelues, <hi>Iob</hi> 31. 1. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 34. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 4.</p>
               <p>Not only fornication and adultery are here forbidden, but alſo all wanton deſires and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, all vnchaſte ſpeeches, ſongs, geſtures, ſporting, and dalliance, with all degrees, allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and occaſions of wantonneſſe, to the corrupting of our ſelues and others, <hi>Gen.</hi> 38. 14. <hi>Gen.</hi> 39. 7. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9. 30. <hi>Prou.</hi> 7. 10, 11, 12. 13. <hi>Matt.</hi> 5. 28. <hi>Mar.</hi> 6. 22. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 22. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 4.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the eighth Commandement?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
               <p>Wee are here commanded to labour with body or minde, for our owne maintenance,
<pb facs="tcp:19946:7"/> and the reliefe of others, <hi>Epheſians</hi> 4. 28. 2 <hi>The.</hi> 3. 10.</p>
               <p>Not only robbing or ſtealing things of value, but alſo the fraudulent taking of any, the leaſt thing that is not ours; all falſe weights and meaſures, bribery, all deceit in bargaining, all gaine with the iniury and hurt of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and all deſires and purpoſes tending thereto, are here forbidden, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 12. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 6.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the tenth Commandement?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The preſeruing of our neighbours good name is here commanded, <hi>Prouerbs</hi> 22. 1. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 3.</p>
               <p>Not onely falſe witneſſe-bearing before a Magiſtrate, but all backbiting, ſlandering, or liſtning to ſlanderers, all hurting of our neighbours good name, all deſires &amp; purpoſes tending thereto, all falſe reports, falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, flattery, and al ſuch lies, are here forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. 1. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19. 16. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 25. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12. 2, 3. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the tenth Commandement?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt not couet, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>All purity of the heart towards our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is here commanded.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:7"/>
               <p> The firſt motions of ſin againſt our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, euen without the conſent of the will are here forbidden, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 7.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> I heare no mention of the ſin of drunkennes, doth no commandement forbid this ſin?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, for drunkennes is a cauſe of many ſins, and drunkards ſin either directly or by conſequence againſt euery Commandement.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How ſin they againſt the firſt, ſecond, third, and fourth Commandements?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They loue pleaſures more then God, they neglect the outward ſeruice of God, they are commonly great ſwearers, and Sabbath breakers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How ſin they againſt the Commandements of the ſecond table?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They diſobey pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, maſters, Magiſtrates and Miniſters, they often brawle and fight, and ſometimes kill or wound; many of them reſort to wicked houſes, not only for drinke, but for whoredome alſo. They deceiue their Creditors, and begger their owne wiues and Children. They are railers and ſlanderers, all concupiſcence raignes in them, and they omit all maner of duties to God and their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> But who are drunkards?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:8"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not only they that reele, or are void of reaſon, but all riotous and idle tipling Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, that for loue of drinke do liue in the forenamed ſins, or in any of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Thou ſaidſt, that the Law is a ſchoole-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to bring vs vnto Chriſt, if we can make right vſe of it. Shew me then what vſe is to be made of theſe Commandements?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By theſe, the wicked are taught to ſee and diſcerne their owne wickedneſſe, in that they doe not keepe any of Gods Lawes, nor truly endeuour to keepe them, but that they daily and hourely rebell againſt God, and ſo are vnder the power of ſinne and Satan their maſter, and in the ready way to be damned for euer with him, <hi>Romans</hi> 3. 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 1, 2. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 4. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 26. <hi>Deut.</hi> 27. 26.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Yea, but this Doctrine is grieuous and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So it is to the wicked, but it is whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for them if they will receiue it; for vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſorrow is the onely way to true comfort: If we labour and bee heauy laden with our ſinnes, Chriſt inuiteth vs to come vnto him, wlth promiſe to eaſe vs, <hi>Matthew</hi> 11. 28. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 16. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 15.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> After that we are come vnto Chriſt, is there no more vſe to be made of theſe Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, for they ſerue as a rule to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whereby they meaſure all their actions, yea, their words, and al their inward thoughts and affections, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. 21, 22, 23. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 11. and 119. 1, 9. and where they finde themſelues to ſwarue and decline, though neuer ſo little, from this rule, they bewaile their infirmity, and ſtir vp their repentance, 2 <hi>Sa.</hi> 24. 10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 75. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 22, 23.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How doth the Law of God bring a man vnto Chriſt?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By ſhewing him his miſery, that hee may ſue to Chriſt for mercy, <hi>Matt.</hi> 9. 12.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> And what then doth Chriſt for him?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He worketh in him true repentance and a liuely faith,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is true repentance?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a ſupernaturall change of the heart, and of the thoughts, words and deeds, from infidelity to faith, from diſobedience to obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience &amp; from all ſins to the contrary vertues, <hi>Math.</hi> 3. 2. and 4. 17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 2 <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 22. <hi>&amp;c Math.</hi> 3. 8. <hi>Acts</hi> 26. 18.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. What is a liuely faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:9"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> A ſupernaturall gift of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 19. 20. and 2. 8. <hi>Math.</hi> 16. 17. whereby a ſinner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing Gods promiſes in Chriſt, is vnited with him, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. 33, 56. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15. 5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 3, &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 22. 23 Hoſ. 2. 19. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 30. is iuſtified and ſanctfied <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. 6. <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 9 and draweth neere to God for deliuerance from all euil, and the obtayning of all good. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1. 2 <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. 12 <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 16 and 10. 22. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> On whom is this gift bestowed?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Only vpon the elect, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 48. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12. 39, 40.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How is faith wrought?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By Gods Word and Spirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How by the Word?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Gods Word ſheweth vs, whence and how grieuouſly we haue fallen, and what meanes God hath ordained to reſtore vs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 16. and 10. 17.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How by the Spirit?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt worketh effectually on them that are to be ſaued, inlightning their darke mindes, ſoftning their hard hearts, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them cleerely to diſcerne, and carefully to regard the things which the word teacheth; to tremble at Gods iuſtice, and their owne hainous deſerts; highly to prize Chriſt the
<pb facs="tcp:19946:9"/> Redeemer, to eſteem all things droſſe &amp; dung in compariſon of him, &amp; neuer to reſt till God by Chriſt hath receiued them into fauour, <hi>Act.</hi> 16. 14. <hi>Ier.</hi> 31. 33. <hi>Eze.</hi> 11. 19. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. 44, 45. <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. 6.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> In what caſe are they that heare the Word without this working of the Spirit?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Seeing they ſee not, hearing they heare not, they diſcerne not their owne filthineſſe, nor the wrath of God abiding on them; they value Chriſt beneath their earthly riches and pleaſures, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. 3, 4. <hi>Eſ.</hi> 6. 9. <hi>Matt.</hi> 13. 13. <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. 22. <hi>Mark.</hi> 5. 17. <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is their eſtate in whom God by his Word and Spirit worketh this faith?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By this faith they receiue Chriſt, they liue the life of grace, they are iuſtified, and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, they pleaſe God, they are made the children of God, they ouercom the world and the deuill, and obtaine eternall ſaluation, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. 12. <hi>Hab.</hi> 2. 4. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. 6. <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 9. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 5, 6. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 4. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 16. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 9.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> But many that beleeue, liue wickedly, and are ouercome of the world and the deuill.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They haue but an hiſtoricall faith, a dead faith, a faith of deuils, which cannot profit them, <hi>I am.</hi> 2. 14, 19, 26.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are the things which thou doeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I beleeue whatſoeuer is contained in the Scriptures, the chiefe points whereof are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Articles of the Chriſtian ſaith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Rehearſe thoſe Articles.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I beleeue in God the Father Almightie, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What learneſt thou in generall out of theſe Articles?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Three things. 1. How to beleeue rightly. 2. How to liue godly. 3. How to cheere vp my heart ioyfully.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Firſt then ſhew me how thou learneſt hence to beleeue rightly: &amp; that thou mayſt proceede in order, tell me how theſe Articles may be diuided.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Into foure parts. 1. Wee are taught what to beleeue concerning God the Father: 2. Concerning God the Sonne: 3. Concerning God the Holy Ghoſt: 4 Concerning Gods Church, and the priuiledges thereto belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Seeing there is but one God, why nameſt thou Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe three ſeuerall perſons are all but one and the ſame God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 4. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. 16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 13. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 7.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> VVhat meanest <note place="margin">A more exact definition, but obſcure, is this. A perſon is a ſubſtance reaſonable, incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable, whole, and not ſubſiſting in another: Therefore no qualitie, and nothing void of life or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, is a perſon. God or man, or Angell in generall is no perſon. Mans body alone, or his ſoule alone; or Chriſts man-hood without his God-head, is no perſon.</note> 
                  <hi>thou by a perſon?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> One man, as <hi>Peter,</hi> one Angell, as <hi>Gabriel</hi> is a perſon: So in the God-head, the FATHER is One Perſon, the SONNE Another, &amp; the HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY GHOST Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtinct Perſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the firſt part of the Creed?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I beleeue in God the Father Almighty, maker of heauen and earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What meaneſt thou by this, I beleeue in God?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This I meane, Gods Spirit aſſureth me that God loueth me, and will bleſſe me both in this world and in the world to come, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 15, 16. <hi>Galat.</hi> 2. 20. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 8. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 8.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whoſe Father is God?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Father of Chriſt, and of all the faithfull, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20. 17.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What beleeueſt thou of this God &amp; Fathers</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That he is a Spirit, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. 24. infinite in power, and likewiſe in wiſdome, juſtice, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, truth, and euery way, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 1. <hi>Exo.</hi> 3. 14.
<pb facs="tcp:19946:11"/> 
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. 6. <hi>Iob</hi> 12. 13. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 17. and 6. 15, 16.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How doth this appeare?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In that he made heauen, earth, and all therein, all of nothing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 1. all very good, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 31. and all for his owne glory, <hi>Prou.</hi> 16. 4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 33.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> If God made all good, how is it that deuils and vngodly men are ſo wicked?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God made them good, but by their fall they haue made themſelues wicked, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8. 44. <hi>Iude</hi> 6. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 31. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 6.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How doth it further appeare that God is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In that he gouerneth the world and all things therein by his wonderfull prouidence, <hi>Prou.</hi> 16. 33. <hi>Matt.</hi> 10. 29, 30.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> If God doth gouerne all by his prouidence, how is it that the godly oft mourne, and the wicked oft reioyce?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God wil turn the ſorrowes of the godly into ioy, and the ioyes of the wicked into ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, <hi>Luke</hi> 6. 20. 24. <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 25. <hi>Iohn</hi> 16. 20. and in the meane time, the godly doe profit by their afflictions, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 67, 71. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 17, 18. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12. 11.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Rehearſe the ſecond part of the Creede.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> And in Ieſus Chrſt, that is, I beleeue in
<pb facs="tcp:19946:11"/> Ieſus Chriſt his only Sonne our Lord, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is Ieſus Chriſt?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God Almighty, and man conſiſting of ſoule and body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why muſt he be God?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That he might be able of himſelfe to ſatisfie Gods iuſtice for all our ſinnes, to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit heauen for vs, to ſend vs the Holy Ghoſt, to ouercome ſinne, death, Satan, tyrants, and all the mighty enemies of his Church, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 98. 1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 25. <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 28.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why muſt he be man?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That he might ſuffer for man, and that he might pittie vs, hauing had experience of our miſeries, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 16, 17, 18. and 4. 15.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which Perſon of the three became man?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God the Sonne, the ſecond Perſon in the Trinitie, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. 14. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 16.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What doth IESVS <hi>ſignifie?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Sauiour, becauſe he only ſaueth his people from their ſinnes, <hi>Matth.</hi> 1. 21. <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 12.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What doth Meſſiah or Chriſt ſignifie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Anointed, for God by his Spirit an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointed Him to bee our King to gouerne vs, our Prieſt to offer vp Himſelfe for a Sacrifice, and to make interceſſion for vs, our Prophet
<pb facs="tcp:19946:12"/> to declare Gods will vnto vs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 33. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 4. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 61. 1. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 15. That he might make vs alſo kings and prieſts vnto God, and inable vs to inſtruct others in the will of God, <hi>Reu.</hi> 1. 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 14.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How is Chriſt Gods only Sonne, ſince all the faithfull are his children?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God is the Father of Chriſt by nature, and our Father by grace, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. 16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 5, 6. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 18.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why addest thou, Our LORD?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He hath created and redeemed vs, he is our beſt and greateſt Maſter, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 95. 6, 7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 5, 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 8, 9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 19. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 36.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What beleeueſt thou concerning Chriſts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception and birth?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That he was borne of a mother, without a Father miraculouſly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why ſo?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That hee might not be conceiued and borne in ſinne as we are, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 15. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 19.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q</hi> How diuideſt thou the Articles that follow concerning Chriſt?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They containe partly his humiliation, and partly his exaltation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Rehearſe thoſe Articles that containe his humiliation.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He ſuffered vnder <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, dead and buried, he deſcended into hel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Did Chriſt, when he liued vpon the earth, liue in pompe, riches, eaſe and pleaſures?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No: but in pouerty, labour and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Eſay</hi> 53. 1, 1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. 20. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What death died he, and how?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> His enemies of malice accuſed him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> the Iudge, who to pleaſure them, condemned him to death, euen to the bitter, ſhamefull, &amp; curſed death of the Croſſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 13. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 8.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Died he willingly or againſt his will?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Moſt willingly, becauſe he knew that God his Father had ſo decreed, and becauſe his purpoſe was by his owne death to kill ſinne in vs, and ſaue vs from eternall death, ſhame and torment, <hi>Romans</hi> 6. 6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 14. 15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 14.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What beleeueſt thou concerning his buriall and his deſcending into hell?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To aſſure vs of his death, his body was buried, and continued till the third day vnder the dominion of death, that he might deliuer vs from the-dominion thereof, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 14, 15.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Rehearſe the Articles that containe Chriſts exaltation.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The third day he roſe againe from the dead, he aſcended into heauen, and ſitteth on the right hand of God the Father Almightie, from thence ſhall he come to iudge the quick and the dead.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What beleeueſt thou heere?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That by the power of his Godhead, he raiſed his dead body to life againe the third day, and that, a glorious life, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10. 18. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 18. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why did he ſo?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That hee might ſhew the ſame power on vs, by raiſing our ſoules now from ſin, and our bodies hereafter from the graue, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 20. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Goe on to his Aſcenſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Forty daies after his Reſurrection, he aſcended viſibly in ſoule and body into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why did he ſo?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That we whiles we line, may through his quickning ſpirit, aſcend by heauenly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 1, 2. that at our death, our ſoules may aſcend and be with Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 23. <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 22. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 14. 13. <hi>Luke</hi> 23. 43 and that
<pb facs="tcp:19946:13"/> at the laſt day, we may both in ſoule and body aſcend and liue with him for euer, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14. 2. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 17.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How doth Chriſt ſit at Gods right hand? hath God the Father a right hand and a left, and other parts of a mans body, as many imagine?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Their imagination is fooliſh and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: for his ſitting there doth ſignifie, that the ſame Chriſt that was ſo greatly humbled, is now exalted aboue all men and Angels, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 20, 21, 22.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What profit haue we thereby?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This, that he can and doth defend vs from all enemies, maketh interceſſion for vs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 31, 34. and ſendeth vs the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16. 7. <hi>Acts.</hi> 2. 33. and the Miniſters of his Word, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 18. 19. 20. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4. 10. 11.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What beleeueſt thou concerning his comming to Iudgement.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He will come from heauen in glory, with all his holy Angels, and all men ſhal giue account to him, of all their thoughts, words and deeds, <hi>Matthew</hi> 25. 31. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 10. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. 36. <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 31. <hi>Eccles.</hi> 12. 14.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the third part of the Beleefe?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I beleeue in the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the Holy Ghoſt?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:14"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> God, the third perſon in Trinity, <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 3, 4. proceeding from the Father and the Son <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15. 26. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 6. who doth direct, ſanctifie, and comfort the faithfull, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16. 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 4. and 8. 9, &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 22. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14. 16.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Of theſe three Perſons, is any one greater then another, or in time before another?</head>
               <p>A. No: but they are all equall &amp; coeternall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Rehearſe the fourth part of the Beleefe.</head>
               <p>A. I belieue the holy Catholick Church, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is this holy Catholike Church?</head>
               <p>A. The whole number of thoſe, whom God, before the world began, decreed to ſanctifie in this life, and to glorifie in the next life, with Chriſt their Head, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 4, 5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 25, 26, 27.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What hath God decreed of the reſt of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde?</head>
               <p>A. To let them runne on in the courſe of ſinne, vnto endleſſe damnation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 13, 22.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> If God hath of old decreed euery mans ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation or damnation, then a man elected ſhall be ſaued, liue he neuer ſo wickedly, and areprobate ſhall be damned, liue he neuer ſo godly?</head>
               <p>A. It is a fooliſh and a wicked thing to imagine that any reprobate can liue or die godly, or that God will ſuffer any of his elect to liue and die wickedly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How then conceiueſt thou of this matter?</head>
               <p>A. Thus, that God in ordaining the end, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daineth fit meanes withall: therefore he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeth, that the elect, by faith and the fruits thereof, ſhal obtaine ſaluation; as the reprobate by their infidelity and the fruits thereof, do purchaſe their owne damnation; <hi>Eſay</hi> 38. 5, 21 <hi>Matth.</hi> 2. 13. <hi>Acts</hi> 27. 24, 31. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16. 16.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Proceede to the priuiledges of the Church: what beleeueſt thou concerning the Communion of Saints?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This Church or body of Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of many members, all which receiue the ſame ſpirituall life from their head, and are helpfull as fellow members one to another, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 4, 5, 6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 26.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What further beleeueſt thou?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That euery Saint hath all his ſinnes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen him by the death of Chriſt, and ſhall at the laſt day riſe againe with his owne body, and liue for euer with Chriſt in heauen in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect happineſſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 34.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> If it ſhal be thus only with Saints, what then ſhall become of the wicked, which are by farre the greater number?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They alſo ſhall riſe againe, euery one of them with his owne body, but to this end, to
<pb facs="tcp:19946:15"/> be tormented in hell for euer with the deuill and his angels, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 41.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Hitherto thou haſt ſhewed how this Creede teacheth vs to beleeue rightly: ſhew further how thou art taught by the ſame to liue godly: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare this out of the firſt part.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He that truly beleeueth that God is his Almightie Father, will truly loue, feare, obey, and truſt in him, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 6. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 14, 17. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 32. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 7. he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble his Father in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 1. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 24. he will pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently beare all his corrections, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Declare this in the ſecond part.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He that beleeueth that Chriſt died for him and roſe againe, by the ſame power and ſpirit of Chriſt, working in him, dieth daily vnto ſin, and is quickned vnto righteouſneſſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 4. and 6. 3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Declare this in the third part.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He that truly beleeueth in the Holy Ghoſt, findeth himſelfe to be anointed and ſealed by him, and that he hath receiued him of God as a pledge of his ſaluation, 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 1. 21, 22. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 13, 14.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Proceede to the fourth part.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He that is a member of Chriſts myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb facs="tcp:19946:15"/> body, muſt and will ſhew by his conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, that Chriſt liueth in him; he that is a Saint will loue Saints intirely, and helpe them to his power; hee that hath his ſinnes forgiuen him, and is waſhed by the bloud of Chriſt, will not returne with the dogge to his vomit, and with the ſow to wallow in the mire, but will wait earneſtly for a glorious Reſurrection and Aſcenſion, he will not for the ſhort and imperfect pleaſures, riches and honours of this life, loſe thoſe perfect and endleſſe ioyes, which God hath prepared for him in heauen, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 20, 21.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Thou ſaidſt that by this Creede thou art taught to cheere vp thy heart with ioy: declare this in the firſt part.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God is my Almighty Father, by this I am more happy than if any earthly king were my father. What riches, what honour, what delight, what other good thing can I want that he ſeeth expedient for me, <hi>Eſay</hi> 49. 15. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 11. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 7. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12 32. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 17. his wiſedome is my directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his power is my protection, againſt the craft and power of all mine enemies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Declare this in the ſecond part.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt died for me, roſe againe and
<pb facs="tcp:19946:16"/> aſcended into heauen for mee, and now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth interceſſion for mee, my SAVIOVR and none other ſhall be my Iudge, what need I then feare affliction, or ſinne, or hell or death? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 31. <hi>to</hi> 39.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Proceed to the third and fourth part.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All wicked men and deuils cannot grieue me, ſo much as the Holy Ghoſt can and doth comfort mee: I am a member of the Church Chriſts myſticall body; what ſinnes, what ſorrows, what enemies bodily or ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly can rent me aſunder from my Head?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Goe on to the Communion of Saints and the reſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Though I am a ſinner, yet am I alſo a Saint: all Saints on earth pray for me, as I do for them, effectually. All Saints that know my eſtate, are ready to helpe and comfort mee, as I am to helpe and comfort them; my ſinnes are waſhed away by the bloud of Chriſt; I ſhall riſe gloriouſly, I ſhall aſcend with Chriſt triumphantly, and with him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy for euer thoſe ioyes which my dull heart cannot now conceiue, nor yet the leaſt part of them. Euen ſo, come LORD IESVS.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Then thou esteemeſt this faith of thine, to be an ineſtimable treaſure?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:16"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yea verily, for without this faith, if I had millions of wealth, I ſhould be moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy, and in the way to endleſſe and intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſhame and torments; but with this faith though pouertie, ſickneſſe, perſecution, and al temporall croſſes light vpon me, yet haue I great cauſe to reioice in God, who is my por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How is this faith of thine preſerued and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By Prayer, by the Sacraments, and by continuall meditation in the Word of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Rehearſe the Lords Prayer.</head>
               <p>A. Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why is it called the Lords Prayer?</head>
               <p>A. Becauſe Chriſt, our Lord and Maſter, taught it vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What gather we hence?</head>
               <p>A. Great comfort, in that the Sonne of God himſelf hath framed and indighted our petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for vs, and is euer ready to preſent vs and our prayers before God his Father.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How may it be fitly diuided?</head>
               <p>A. Into a preface, petitions, &amp; a concluſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the Preface?</head>
               <p>A. Our Father which art in Heauen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What learnest thou by this Preface?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:17"/>
               <p> A. I learne foure things: Firſt, that wee muſt pray for others as well as for our ſelues, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 18. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 1.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that God is a louing Father to the godly, and willing to helpe them, <hi>Eſay</hi> 49. 15. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 13. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 11.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that God is a heauenly and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull Father, able to helpe his children, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 51. 12, 13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115 3. and therefore we muſt pray in faith and full aſſurance to be heard.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, that we muſt not pray with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane, carnall, and earthly hearts, but with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence to Gods Maieſty, and with heauenly affections, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 28. 16, 17. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8. 22. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11. 41.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How many petitions are there in the Lords Prayer?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Six.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What deſireſt thou in the three firſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thoſe things which belong immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What deſireſt thou in the three laſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thoſe things that are needfull for our ſelues, both for body and ſoule.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the firſt petition?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:17"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> Hallowed be thy Name.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What deſire we in this petition?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, that God may haue praiſe for all his worthineſſe; as for his power, wiſdome, iuſtice, and mercy, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. 6, 7. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. 10, 11, 12. <hi>Reu.</hi> 4. 8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>Reu.</hi> 5. 12, 13.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that God may haue thankes for all his benefits; as for our health and peace, food and rayment, for our election, creation, redemption, vocation, aſſurance of glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and for the comfort of his moſt holy word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. and 104. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. 9. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 20.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the ſecond petition?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thy Kingdome come.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What deſire we in this petition?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, wee deſire that God would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the wicked, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 13. and 67. 2. <hi>Matt.</hi> 3. 2. and 4. 17.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that God would increaſe his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the godly, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 17, 18, 19. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. 16 17, 18, 19.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that God would aduance his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, by ſending godly Magiſtrates and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and ſpecially by Chriſts comming to iudgement, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 9. 38. <hi>Reu.</hi> 23. 20.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the third petition?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:18"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thy will be done in earth, as it is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What deſire we in this petition?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We pray that God would enable vs, to walke in the way of all his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: And that Magiſtrates and people, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and hearers, husbands and wiues, parents and children, maſters and ſeruants, may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme thoſe duties of their ſeuerall callings, which they owe one to another, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 1. and 5. 21, 22, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What meane theſe words, In earth as it is in heauen?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Wee deſire grace to doe Gods will gladly and cheerfully, as the Angels in heauen doe the ſame, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 20, 21.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the fourth petition?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Giue vs this day our daily bread.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What deſire we in this petition?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We pray, that God would giue vs food, raiment, health, peace, and all things needfull for this preſent life. That he would ſtirre vs vp to labour and diligence, that hee would keepe vs from ſloth and idleneſſe, and giue a bleſſing to our honeſt endeuors.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What learneſt thou further from the words of this petition?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:18"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, that whatſoeuer wee lawfuly poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe, is Gods gift, <hi>Deuteronomie</hi> 8. 17, 18. <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bac.</hi> 1. 16.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that we muſt haue a feeling of other mens wants, as well as of our owne, and ſhew it by charitable deeds, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 3.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that if we haue maintenance only for the time preſent, and none for the time to come, we muſt bee content, and depend on Gods prouidence, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 25.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, that although we liue not in eaſe, plenty, and pleaſure, yet if we haue things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, we muſt be content, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. 20. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 8.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the fift petition?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, as wee forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What deſire we in this petition?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We pray that God would forgiue vs all our ſinnes, originall and actuall, of commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and omiſſion, ſecret and open, whether knowne or vnknowne euen to our ſelues, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 12.</p>
               <p>And that he would not only pardon our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deeds, but all our wicked, vnprofitable, and idle words, all our ſinfull purpoſes, and all our deſires, ioyes, feares and griefes, that are againſt
<pb facs="tcp:19946:19"/> the loue of God and of our neighbour, <hi>Ecc.</hi> 11. 9. and 12. 14. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. 36.</p>
               <p>And further, that God would giue vs grace, truly to examine our ſelues, to diſcerne our ſinnes, to confeſſe them, to hate and forſake them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this added, As we forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To teach vs to forgiue all wrongs, to end our quarrels, and to be free from malice, or elſe God will not forgiue vs, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 23. and 6. 14, 15. and 18. 23.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the ſixt petition?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> And lead vs not into tentation, but deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs from euill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What deſire we in this petition?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We pray that God would not ſuffer the deuill, nor the world to preuaile againſt vs, nor our owne corruptions to preuaile within vs, but that he would giue vs ſtrength to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 22. and 6. 10, 11. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 4. That we may be wiſe to diſcerne when Satan tempteth vs to thoſe things which ſeeme to be no ſinnes, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. 3, 6. or when he vſeth our owne friends for his inſtruments to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue vs, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 22, 23.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the concluſion of the Lords praier?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:19"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> For thine is the Kingdome, the power and the glory, for euer and euer, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the meaning of this concluſion?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe God is our gracious King, and carefull for his ſubiects, and ſeeing his power is ſuch, that he can giue vs all good things, and defend vs from all euill, 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 29. 10, 11. 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 20. 6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62. 11. &amp; 115. 1. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 17. <hi>Reu.</hi> 4. 11 and 5. 12, 13.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing the things we haue prayed for, are for his owne glory, therefore we earneſtly deſire, and ſtedfaſtly beleeue that he wil grant them vnto vs. <hi>Amen</hi> let it be ſo, yea without doubt it ſhall be ſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How doe the wicked pray this prayer?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They ſhew their vile hypocriſie in euery part thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How doe they ſhew their hypocriſie in the preface?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They call God Father, and yet haue no aſſurance of his loue, nor care to pleaſe him, but ſhew themſelues to be his enemies, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the deuill, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8. 44. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 8.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How doe they ſhew their hypocriſie in the three firſt petitions?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They diſhonour God, they deſpiſe his iuſtice, power and prouidence.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:20"/>
               <p> They take part with euill men in euill cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſo contend and fight for Satan and his kingdome, againſt Chriſt and his ſubiects, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 1, 2, 3. <hi>Luk.</hi> 19. 14.</p>
               <p>They reiect Gods will, and doe their own, they follow their owne luſts, they imitate not Angels in heauen, but beaſts on earth, or deuils in hel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How doe they ſhew their hypocriſie in the reſt of the petitions?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Daily bread contents them not, their wealth is euill gotten, or euill ſpent.</p>
               <p>They aske pardon of ſinne, but haue no purpoſe nor deſire to leaue the ſame.</p>
               <p>They forgiue not wrongs receiued, but beare malice againſt Gods children, which haue not wronged them.</p>
               <p>They are not wary againſt temptations, but run on boldly: thus their prayer is contrary to the whole courſe of their life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Then none but a ſincere Chriſtian truly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and conuerted, can pray this prayer or the like, with vnderſtanding, and with an vnfained deſire?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is euen ſo, and therefore this prayer being rightly vnderſtood, is a perfect tryall of a mans true conuerſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 15, 16.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Thou ſaiſt that thy faith is preſerued and increaſed by the Sacrament: what is a Sacrament?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Gods ſeale of his couenant made with the faithfull and their ſeed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> In this Couenant, what doth God vndertake on his part?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To defend the faithfull in all dangers, to giue them all good things expedient for them, to cauſe all things to worke for their good, and to crowne them with eternal glory, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. 1. and 17. 1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. 11. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 28.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What doe the faithfull vndertake for their part?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not to follow their owne luſts, nor the worlds allurements, nor euil examples, nor the deuils tentations, but readily to obey all Gods Commandements, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, &amp;c. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 11, 12. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 1, 2. <hi>Luc.</hi> 1. 72, 73, 74, 75.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How many Sacraments be there?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two: Baptiſme, and the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is Baptiſme?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Gods ſeale, whereby we enter into Couenant with him, by the waſhing of our ſoules from ſinne through Chriſts bloud, as
<pb facs="tcp:19946:21"/> our bodies are waſhed with water, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 26. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 5. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 12.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the Lords Supper?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Gods ſeale, wherby we renue our Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with him, whereby our ſoules are nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and comforted with the body and bloud of Chriſt, as our bodies are with the Bread and Wine, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 16. and 11. 24, 25. 26.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Doe all that come to the Lords Supper re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue profit thereby?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No: for all vnworthy receiuers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue much hurt thereby, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 17, 27, 29.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Who are vnworthy receiuers?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. All that are carnall and vnregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The godly themſelues, when they come with ſecurity, hauing offended God, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting to renue their repentance, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. 27. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 30.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How muſt thou prepare thy ſelfe for the Lords Supper?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I muſt examine my ſelfe,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether I repent me truly of all my ſinnes paſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether I ſtedfaſtly purpoſe to leade a new life.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19946:21"/> 3. Whether I haue a liuely faith in Gods mercy through Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether I remember and meditate on Chriſts death with thankfulneſſe.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whether I be in charitie with all men, freely forgiuing them all wrongs done againſt me, as God for Chriſts ſake hath freely forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Thou ſaiſt that thy faith is preſerued and increaſed by continuall meditation in the Word of God: ſhew me then to what end, and in what manner oughteſt thou both to reade Gods word, and to heare it preached?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not for faſhions ſake to ſeeme religious, but with a ſincere purpoſe, earneſt deſire, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant endeuour, and feruent prayer, that thereby my faith may bee ſtrengthened, my life amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and my ſoule comforted, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 3. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.</p>
               <p>And further, I muſt beware of malice againſt the Preacher, and of a preiudicate opinion of his perſon or gifts, of pride and ſelfewill; I muſt reade and heare with an humble heart: ſo that when the Word ſheweth me any errour of mine, in iudgement or practice, on the right hand, or on the left, I muſt bee readie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 1, 2. <hi>Iames</hi> 1. 21, 22. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What if the Preacher deliuer things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound or vnprofitable?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I muſt pray, that I may with wiſdome diſcerne, and with modeſty refuſe the ſame; but euer I muſt beware, that I bee not a raſh and proud cenſurer of any man, ſpecially of Gods meſſengers, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 21. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 1. <hi>Iam.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>Iam.</hi> 1. 19, 20.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How oughteſt thou to prepare thy ſelfe for death at all times, &amp; ſpecially in time of ſicknes?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> After the ſame manner as I ought to prepare my ſelfe to receiue the Lords Supper, ſo that if I recouer, I muſt walke the more cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectly afterward.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb facs="tcp:19946:22"/>
            <head>MORNING PRAYER for a Family.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A briefe Confeſſion with thanksgiuing.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE moſt humbly preſent our ſelues, O LORD, before the Throne of thy great Maieſty, in the name of thy beloued Sonne our onely Sauiour, confeſſing that of our ſelues we are moſt vile, polluted with ſinnes originall and actuall, ſinnes againſt thee and againſt our neighbour, ſins of omiſſion and commiſſion, ſecret and open, known and vnknown euen to our ſelues. O let them not make a ſeparation betwixt thee and vs, ſeeing thou art reconciled vnto vs, and not onely ſo, but alſo thou haſt vouchſafed to become our louing Father, hauing redeemed vs by thy Sonnes bloud, and adopted vs by his Spirit, whom thou haſt ſent into our hearts: thou haſt alſo fed, clothed, and lodged vs, thou haſt ſtrengthned and preſerued vs euen to this
<pb facs="tcp:19946:23"/> houre; therefore for all thy mercies ſo many and ſo great, we praiſe and bleſſe thy holy name. And now, Lord, as thou haſt raiſed our bodies from ſleepe, ſo raiſe vp our hearts from their naturall dulneſſe and earthly diſpoſition: Sanctifie vs more and more in ſoule and body, that euery day wee may grow in grace, and in the knowledge of Chriſt, by the workes of the Spirit.</p>
               <p>O Lord increaſe our faith, giue vs yet more aſſurance of that thy <note place="margin">Prayer for ſtrength of faith.</note> eternall loue, that therein we may reioyce with ioy vnſpeakable and glorious, and obediently wait for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of all thy promiſes, both to prouide for vs, and to defend vs in this life, and after to crowne vs with eternall glorie. Let this aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance bee ſuch, that thereby we may bee able to endure al the miſeries and trials of this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall pilgrimage, not only with patience and quietneſſe, but alſo with heauenly comfort.</p>
               <p>And teach vs, O Lord, to loue thee, and that ſincerely, that our <note place="margin">Prayer for loue to God.</note> falſe hearts may not goe a who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring after the world, whiles wee fooliſhly and wickedly admire the riches, and pleaſures, and pride of this life, and ſuffer our ſelues to be
<pb facs="tcp:19946:23"/> ſnared therewith. O let vs know, that the loue of thy glorious Maieſtie, and of theſe vile things, cannot ſtand together. As wee deſire to loue thee ſincerely, ſo to loue thee abundantly, that wee may bee the better aſſured that wee loue thee, let not our loue bee as a ſparke of fire couered with the aſhes of our darke and earthly corruptions, but let it be as burning coles, and as a vehement flame.</p>
               <p>And let it appeare by our hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie loue to our neighbour, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <note place="margin">Prayer for loue to our neighbour.</note> to thoſe, whoſe good fruits declare them to be thy faithfull children. Suffer vs not this day, nor heereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to be iniurious to any by deceit or oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by ſlandering or back-biting thoſe that are abſent, by reproching or diſgracing thoſe that are preſent, or by any other wrongs, but let vs be profitable and helpfull to many, to the vttermoſt of our power. Grant that wee may inſtruct thoſe that are more ignorant then our ſelues, let vs relieue, according as thou haſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled vs, thoſe that ſtand in need of our helpe.</p>
               <p>O Lord, preſerue vs from the damnable error of thoſe that <note place="margin">Againſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfet happines</note> place their greateſt happineſs in worldly wealth and pleaſure, open our eyes to
<pb facs="tcp:19946:24"/> diſcerne yet more cleerely, that if thou be our riches, then wee ſhal be rich indeed, if thou be our delight, then ſhall we perceiue how vile and vaine all carnall delights are: Let vs know how good a thing it is to draw neer vnto thee, by hearing thy voyce in thy moſt holy Word, and by ſpeaking to thee in our prayers and thankſgiuing; withdraw not thy Spirit from vs, giue vs not ouer vnto Satan and worldly luſts, for then ſhall we runne headlong into all ſinne and miſery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>This that followeth, is verie needfull in many houſes of the Gentrie and richer ſort.</head>
               <p>LOrd, preſerue this family from the ſinnes of idleneſſe, pride, fulneſſe of bread, from contempt or neglect of the poore, from fooliſh and corrupt communication, from chambering and wantonneſſe, from exceſſiue and vnſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable eating and drinking, from louing of pleaſures more than thee, the chiefeſt Good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:24"/>
               <head>In a meane and laborious Family, prayer to this purpoſe will be conuenient.</head>
               <p>WEE beſeech thee cheere vs vp, and comfort vs in the middeſt of our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and trauels, let vs not admire or enuie the happineſſe of thoſe that abound with eaſe and wealth, but euer let vs remember, that a painefull and godly life is the way to perfect reſt and endleſſe ioy, that an idle, voluptuous, and vnprofitable life, is the way to bitter and endleſſe pain, that thou didſt conſecrate Chriſt Ieſus the Prince of our ſaluation, through affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, that they are bleſſed that mourne, for they ſhall be comforted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>In what family ſoeuer, thus proceed.</head>
               <p>O Gracious Father, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy loue and thy <note place="margin">Prayer for earthly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings.</note> mercifull promiſes in Chriſt, vouchſafe vnto vs now and hereafter, that meaſure of wealth, and ſuch health, peace, liberty, and credit, as may bee moſt expedient for vs in our ſeuerall callings, and for the better diſcharge of our dutie to thee and our brethren.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:25"/>
               <p> Lord preſerue and direct thy Vniuerſall Church, giue <note place="margin">For the Church <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſall.</note> thy Goſpell free paſſage, let thy power and wiſdome confound the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full might and policies of the enemies of thy truth, remoue all ſtumbling blocks, and knit together thy ſeruants, by the vnitie of the Spirit in the bond of peace.</p>
               <p>Continue thy great mercies on theſe Churches of <hi>England,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">For the Chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> grant that as the ſinnes of all ſorts and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees amongſt vs, haue been many and verie grieuous in thy ſight; ſo our earneſt repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and ſincere humiliation before thee may bee ſuch, that thy terrible iudgements may be ſtayed, before thy wrath breake forth againſt vs.</p>
               <p>Protect with thy proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, direct with thy Spirit, <note place="margin">For the Kings Maieſty, &amp;c.</note> and inrich with thy heauenly grace, our Soueraigne King: be mercifull to the Queene, to Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> to the Prince and Princeſſe Palatine with their iſſue: Indue the honourable priuie Councellors with wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from aboue, giue grace to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, that they may truly and diligently exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute
<pb facs="tcp:19946:25"/> iuſtice and iudgement; to the Biſhops and Miniſters, that they may by diligent and effectuall preaching, and godly example of life, proceed to build vp thy Church amongſt vs; root out idle and idoll ſhepheards, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the number of faithfull Paſtors. Let thy rich bleſſings bee powred downe vpon all ſorts and degrees, to the prayſe of thy Name, through IESVS CHRIST our Lord and Sauiour, in whoſe Name, for theſe and all other good things needfull for vs and all thy ſeruants whoſoeuer, wee pray as he hath taught vs.</p>
               <q>Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</q>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Euening Prayer for a Family.</head>
               <p>O Moſt gracious God, and mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Ieſus Chriſt, we humble our ſelues before thy Maieſty, confeſſing and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing the ſinnes of our whole life, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of this preſent day.</p>
               <p>Pardon, O LORD, our diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered affections, which haue <note place="margin">Prayer for the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſins.</note> beene too carneſtly bent vpon the profits and pleaſures of this preſent life. Forgiue vs whatſoeuer ſinfull
<pb facs="tcp:19946:26"/> anger thou haſt beheld in vs, and our inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate griefe at worldly croſſes, when as we are not duly grieued for our ſins, and the ſins of this Land, and of this age, and for the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our deare brethren. Forgiue our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ioy, which is ſo ſtrong when earthly things anſwere our deſires, and ſo weake and feeble, when we conſider thoſe ſpirituall, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, and eternall bleſſings, wherewith thou haſt bleſſed vs in heauenly things in Chriſt. Paſſe by, whatſoeuer vncharitable, vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, or vnſauoury talke, hath proceeded from any of vs, with neglect of that admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, or inſtruction, or conſolation, which we ſhould haue miniſtred one to another. O pardon, for thy mercy ſake, our neglect and omiſſion of workes of piety towards thee, or of mercy towards our neighbour, and all our idleneſſe.</p>
               <p>O forgiue our exceſſe, and our abuſe, of meat, drinke, ſleepe, recreations, all our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance, and diſordering of minde or body, in making them vnfit for thy ſeruice, and for the duties of our ſeuerall callings. O forgiue thoſe our imperfections and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that are mixt with our beſt actions, and doe defile the ſame.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:26"/>
               <p> And ſpecially forgiue our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe for thy many and <note place="margin">A Thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing.</note> great mercies; grant that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, we may euer ſtirre vp our dull hearts, that they may be inflamed with loue to thee, that haſt elected vs to ſaluation, and created vs after thy owne image, that haſt redeemed vs, with the ineſtimable price of thy deareſt Sonnes bloud, that haſt called vs effectually by thy Word and Spirit, from the power of darkneſſe vnto the kingdome of thy deare Sonne, not only reconciling vs that were thine enemies, but alſo making vs thy deare and glorious children, and heires of thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly kingdome.</p>
               <p>O teach vs to walke worthy <note place="margin">Prayer for diuers gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne.</note> of this vocation whereto thou haſt called vs; inſtruct vs euer by thy Word, worke on our hearts effectually by thy Spirit, that we may diſcerne and daily reforme our grieuous corruptions, that we may not flatter nor pleaſe our ſelues in any of our ſinnes, nor walke on ſecurely and careleſly, but that wee may ſtriue for, and attaine vnto more power to ſubdue and conquer our carnall luſts, to reſiſt the allurements of this world, and the
<pb facs="tcp:19946:27"/> euill examples of the multitude, that we be not any more carried away herewith, as with a violent ſtreame. Open our eyes to diſcerne the nets which Satan laieth to enſnare vs, in eating, in drinking, in talking, in ſporting, in buying, in ſelling, in giuing or receiuing coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, in pleaſing ſome, in offending others, that we might diſpleaſe thy Maieſty, and kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle thy wrath againſt vs.</p>
               <p>And whereas there are ſo many diuerſities of opinions in the world, and yet but one truth, O guide and direct vs in the ſame by thy Spirit of truth; build vs firmely on thy Sonne Chriſt, that ſure foundation. O let vs not depart from any truth, nor bee ſtiffe in any error which we haue held: Let vs not hate thoſe that diſſent from vs in ſome points, yet building their faith on Chriſt; grant that wee may follow the truth in loue, and in all things grow vp vnto CHRIST the Head. Make vs deuout and religious to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee, and obedient to our ſuperiours. Stirre vs vp that we may be helpfull and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to many; Let vs not bee deceitfull, or otherwiſe injurious to any, in word or deed. Make vs charitable, meeke, and patient, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all. Let not our faith be dead, like the
<pb facs="tcp:19946:27"/> faith of Deuils, but a working faith, as the faith of <hi>Abraham</hi> and of <hi>Rahab,</hi> that loued dearely thee and thy children, and ſhewed their faith by their works. Thus let vs walke all our dayes till our change ſhall come. Let our laſt daies be our beſt dayes. Let not the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of death be grieuous or terrible vnto vs. Make vs deſirous to be diſſolued, and to be with Chriſt. Come Lord IESVS, come quickly, perfit thine owne glorie, and thy ſeruants happineſſe.</p>
               <p>In the meane time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in mercie thy deare <note place="margin">Prayer for Gods Church, &amp;c.</note> Spouſe whom thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed with thy precious bloud. Confirme and eſtabliſh thy ſeruants, weaken and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thy foes, confound their malice, their pride and their helliſh plots and deuices. Stir vp thy ſtrength and come and helpe vs. O bleſſe, preſerue, direct and proſper our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne King; be mercifull to the Queene, to our hopefull Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> the Prince and Princeſſe Palatine with their Iſſue, the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Priuy Counſellors, Nobles and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, the Biſhops and Miniſters; the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities and Nurſeries of learning.</p>
               <p>Among all ſorts, ſtirre vp thoſe that may
<pb facs="tcp:19946:28"/> valiantly fight thy battels againſt the Deuill, &amp; againſt this world that lieth in wickednes.</p>
               <p>Be gracious, O Lord, to our <note n="*" place="margin">Parents, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ſiſters, &amp;c.</note>—; to thoſe for whom wee are ſpecially bound to intreate thee, and <note place="margin">They that haue ſuch, may here mention them.</note> whom thou haſt made thy inſtruments of good vnto vs. Protect this family, proſper vs in our health, our credit, and in our worldly eſtate. Aboue all, let vs grow rich in godlineſſe, ſobriety and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Giue vs this night quiet reſt, and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; raiſe vs vp againe in due time, that wee may the next day, and ſo from day to day doe thee acceptable ſeruice, &amp; glorifie thee in our ſeuerall callings: For theſe and for all good things needfull for vs and for al thy children, we pray as thy Sonne our Sauiour hath taught vs. <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer vpon the Lords Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Lord our God, thy Sonne our Sauiour hath aſſured <note place="margin">Vpon the Preface.</note> vs that thou art through him a louing Father to the godly, and willing
<pb facs="tcp:19946:28"/> to helpe them, and that thou art an heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and powerfull Father, alwaies able to comfort them, therefore we come vnto thee with boldneſſe and confidence through faith in him, and we deſire and endeuour to pray vnto thee now and hereafter, not with profane, carnall, and earthly hearts, but with reuerence to thy diuine Maieſty, and with heauenly affections. O helpe vs and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then vs, and raiſe vp our ſoules from earth and earthly things, to thee that dwelleſt on high.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Petition </seg>1</label> Firſt and aboue all things we deſire, that praiſe may be giuen to thee for all thy worthineſſe, that thy ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies may know thee to be the Lord, and themſelues to be but men; that their power is but weakneſſe, and their wiſedome but foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe, when they lift vp themſelues againſt thee and thy deare Spouſe the Church. Get thee honour vpon thine obſtinate enemies, as thou didſt vpon <hi>Pharao</hi> and the Egyptians. But let thy ſeruants and faithful people know thee to their comfort. Let them ſanctifie thee in their hearts, let them euer beleeue and alſo finde by ioyfull experience, that thy power is their protection, thy wiſedome their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,
<pb facs="tcp:19946:29"/> thy iuſtice their deliuerance from all wrongs.</p>
               <p>And let all prayſe and thanks be giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee for all thy benefits, for our health and peace, for our food and raiment, for thy great fauours ſo extraordinary beſtowed vpon this land for many yeares, and for thoſe which we in particular haue receiued, and do inioy from thy bountifull hand, &amp; ſpecially for thoſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly and ſpirituall bleſſings, our election, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, vocation, aſſurance of glorification, and for the comfort of thy moſt holy Word.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Petition </seg>2</label> Let thy Kingdome come; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the wicked, as many as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to thine election, enlighten the eyes of them that are blinded with the loue of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition: grant that thoſe which wallow in ſin, may begin to hate that mire and filth where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they haue delighted. O Lord, increaſe thy gifts and graces in the godly, reigne in them by thy powerfull ſpirit, thou that art the God of peace, ſanctifie them thorowout, that their whole ſpirit, and ſoule, and body, may be kept blameleſs vnto the comming of Ieſus Chriſt. Kill and crucifie in them daily the old man, and let the new man be raiſed vp in them. O Lord, bleſſe and proſper the meanes which
<pb facs="tcp:19946:29"/> thou haſt ordained for theſe euds. Raiſe vp godly Kings, that may walke in the ſteps of <hi>Dauid, Ezekiah, Ioſiah,</hi> and religious Nobles, like <hi>Ioſeph, Obadiah, Daniel, Nehemiah, Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai,</hi> that may adminiſter iuſtice, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine truth, and ſeeke the proſperity of Iſrael-Increaſe, we pray thee, the number of faithfull Paſtors and teachers, endue them with excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent gifts of Learning and Godlineſſe, that they may be able to conuince hereſies and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, to confound euery <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iambres,</hi> that ſhall reſiſt thy truth. O let thy ſeruants walke in the ſteps of the Apoſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and not in pride, couetouſneſſe, or idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Vnite them in thy truth, leſt by their diuiſions thy people be alſo diuided; grant that they may be knit together in one minde and in one iudgement, that with one minde, and with one mouth they may prayſe thy name. And let vs earneſtly wait for thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to iudgement, that thou maiſt put all thine enemies vnder thy feet, and reigne for euer in perfect peace, that wee may reigne with thee triumphantly.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Petition </seg>3</label> In the meane time direct and teach vs to doe thy Holy and bleſſed will, to renounce and denie our owne
<pb facs="tcp:19946:30"/> wills that are ſo fooliſh, ſo peruerſe and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. Teach vs to walke in the way of all thy Commandements; let our hearts be ſeaſoned with godlineſſe, let vs loue thee aboue all, let vs feare thee and euer walke in all ſinceritie as in thy ſight and preſence; let vs truſt in thee, and reſt vpon thy promiſes for the things of this life and of the life to come. Let it be our chiefe delight to ſpeake to thee by prayer and thankſgiuing and to heare thee ſpeaking vnto vs by thy word both read and preached. Inable vs by thy grace to obey thee in thoſe generall duties that belong to all Chriſtians, and in the particular duties of our ſeuerall callings; grant that Magiſtrates and people, Miniſters and hearers, husbands and wiues, parents and children, maſters and ſeruants, may conſcionably, and in heartie obedience vnto thee, performe thoſe duties which they owe one to another. Grant that in whatſoeuer profeſſion, trade or courſe of life thou haſt placed vs, we may not liue to our ſelues, but make this our ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall end, to pleaſe and to glorifie thee.</p>
               <p>And whereas the wicked performe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly duties in earthly manner, defiling their praiers, and thy word &amp; Sacraments by their
<pb facs="tcp:19946:30"/> hypocriſie, grant that we may performe not only heauenly, but alſo earthly duties and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſes in a heauenly manner, walking cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in our vocations, endeuouring with all our might to doe thy Maieſty acceptable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice euery day, and to be through thy grace profitable members of the Church, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and family where we liue. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect vs, and inable vs that we on earth may doe thy worke and buſineſſe wiſely, and alſo gladly and cheerfully, with ſtrength and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, fearing no aduerſary, euer beholding thy face, and following the patterne of thy heauenly Angels.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Petition </seg>4</label> Vouchſafe, O Lord, to giue vs foode, raiment, health, peace; publike and priuate bleſſings, and all things needfull for this preſent life. Stirre vs vp to labour and diligence, keepe vs from ſloth and idleneſſe, giue a bleſſing to our ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours. Let vs neuer goe about to inrich or maintaine our ſelues by lying, by deceit or oppreſſion, or any vnlawfull meanes; let vs ſeeke nothing at the hands of Satan by ſinfull practices or purpoſes, but let our conſciences aſſure vs, that whatſoeuer things we poſſeſſe, are thy good gifts. If we haue gotten any
<pb facs="tcp:19946:31"/> thing wrongfully, giue vs grace to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. Neither pray we againſt our owne wants only, but alſo againſt the wants of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, ſpecially of all thy deare children. O let them ſee and feele thy fatherly affection and prouidence ouer them, and let vs to our power be helpefull vnto them, cutting off all vaine and vicious, all proud and luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous expences, that we may haue the more to beſtow vpon charitable vſes. And though we haue maintenance but for the preſent time, and none for the time to come, let vs be content and depend on thy prouidence; for thou doeſt cloath the Lillies, and feede the Birds, but we are of much more value than they, and the haires of our head are numbred: why ſhould we that are thy flocke, feare either want or other miſeries, ſince it is thy pleaſure to giue vs a Kingdome? Thou that haſt not ſpared thine owne Sonne, but haſt giuen him for vs all vnto the death, how ſhouldeſt thou not with him giue vs all good things alſo? Keepe vs therefore from all pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue and diſtruſtfull cares; let vs remember, that as no man can adde one cubit to his ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo no man can adde one mite to that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of wealth which thou haſt already
<pb facs="tcp:19946:31"/> determined to beſtow vpon euery one. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when wee haue vſed lawfull meanes, and done our due endeuour, let vs quietly commit the ſucceſſe of all vnto thy proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, knowing that thou haſt appointed who ſhall be poore, and who rich, that if thou withholdeſt from vs earthly riches, thou canſt make vs rich in faith, which is farre better. Therefore though we liue not in eaſe, plenty and pleaſure, yet if we haue things neceſſarie, if we haue bread to eat, and clothes to put on, let vs therewith bee content, and the rather, ſeeing that they which ſtriue and toile to bee rich, doe fall into tentations and ſnares, and into many fooliſh and noyſome luſts, which drowne men in perdition and deſtruction. O Lord, we pray thee look with thy eye of pitty and compaſsion, on thoſe that are afflicted with ſickneſſe, giue them patience vnder thy correcting hand, reſtore them to their former health, or elſe prepare them for a better life. Haue pitty on thy ſeruants that are afflicted with grieuous perſecutions, or with horrible warres, and the terrours and calamities that doe accompanie the ſame; O ſtop and ſtay this cruell effuſion of Chriſtian bloud, reſtore peace and tranquillitie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:32"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Petition </seg>5</label> Forgiue wee pray thee our ſinnes and treſpaſſes, our ſinnes originall and actuall, of commiſſion and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, ſecret or manifeſt, our want of loue to thee and our neighbour, our inordinate ſelfe-loue, our dulneſſe and vnaptneſſe vnto things heauenly and ſpirituall, our proneneſſe and forwardneſſe to ſinne and vanity, the faſt cleauing of our affections to the things of this life Pardon, O Lord, all our ſinfull actions, and all our wicked, vnprofitable and idle words, all our ſinfull purpoſes, all our deſires, ioyes, feares, and griefes, that are againſt the loue of thee and of our neighbour: forgiue all our errours, whether in iudgement or in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, whether on the left hand, or on the right. Giue vs grace truly to examine our ſelues, to diſcerne our ſinnes, and to confeſſe them, to hate and to forſake them, yea euen our deareſt ſins, which ſeeme as a right hand, or a right eye vnto vs, let vs not ſpare to chop them off, or to plucke them out, and caſt them from vs. And that our owne malice againſt our neighbours, may not hinder thy mercie towards vs, and our exacting of ſmall debts, cauſe thee to require of vs thoſe ten thouſand talents which wee owe thee, therefore here in
<pb facs="tcp:19946:32"/> thy ſight wee freely forgiue all wrongs and treſpaſſes, we emptie our hearts of the poyſon of malice: if therefore we, whoſe goodnes is but a drop, doe thus behaue our ſelues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them that haue wronged vs, much more thou that art a ſea of goodneſſe and mercie, canſt and wilt pardon vs; and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of let vs bee from thee moſt comfortably aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Petition </seg>6</label> Leade vs not into tentation: let vs not bee puffed vp with worldly proſperity, nor bee ſnared with the baits of ſenſuality, to loue this world and the things therein: let not our belly be our God, let vs not haue our portion in this life. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let vs bee diſmayd with any aduerſitie, let no tribulations turne vs out of the right way: let nothing weaken that conſtant ioy and true happineſſe which wee haue in thee alone. Suffer not Satan to circumuent vs, let vs not be ignorant of his enterpriſes, make vs wiſe to diſcern when he tempteth vs to thoſe things which ſeeme to be no ſinnes, or when hee vſeth our owne deare friends, as <hi>Eue</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Adam,</hi> for his inſtruments to deceiue vs; Lord, thou knoweſt his wiles and his depth; thou, O Sauiour, that haſt thy ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:19946:33"/> encountred with this dreadful enemy, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt that if thou forſakeſt vs, and withdraweſt thy ſelfe from vs, wee ſhall neuer bee able to ſtand againſt him, and againſt all the powers of darkeneſſe. Therefore make vs ſtrong in thee, and in the power of thy might; beſtow vpon vs the whole armour of God, and teach vs to put it on vs and to vſe it, that in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill day we may be able both to reſiſt and to conquer. Make vs wary &amp; watchfull againſt our owne falſe hearts, leſt they betray vs into the hands of Satan: let vs fight mightily euery day againſt our manifold corruptions; let vs be faithfull vnto the death, that wee may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the crowne of life.</p>
               <p>Heare, O Lord, incline thine eares <note place="margin">The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note> to theſe requeſts of vs thy humble ſubiects, for thou art our gracious King, moſt carefull for vs, thou wilt not ſuffer vs to become a prey vnto thine enemies. Thy power is ſuch, that thou canſt giue vs all good things, and defend vs from all euill, and thou knoweſt that the things which we haue prayed for, are for thine owne glorie. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee earneſtly deſire, and ſtedfaſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that thou wilt grant them vnto vs. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> let it be ſo. Yea, without doubt it ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:19946:33"/> bee ſo as we haue prayed: wee beleene, Lord helpe our vnbeleefe.</p>
               <p>Vnto thee, O Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt, be all honour and glory, now and for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A ſhort Morning Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Lord our God, moſt gracious and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Father in Ieſus Chriſt, as thou haſt beſtowed vpon vs innumerable and ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble benefits, ſo vouchſafe, we beſeech thee, to adde this grace and mercy to the reſt, that thou ſtirre vs vp and inable vs by thy holy Spirit, to praiſe and magnifie thy name both for our reſt and ſafetie this night paſt, and for all the reſt of thy mercies. Lord open our eyes, and inlarge our hearts to praiſe thee for the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes, ſo many and ſo hainous, by the bloud of thy Sonne, a price ſo infinite and precious; for our Redemption from the thraldome of Satan, and from thoſe infinite and endleſſe torments which with him we ſhould haue ſuffered, and that by thy Word and thy holy Spirit thou haſt exalted vs to be thy royall children, and heires of thy Kingdome. O giue vs grace this day and euery day to walke worthy of this vocation;
<pb facs="tcp:19946:34"/> renue and quicken our Repentance, humble our hearts with the ſight of our ſinnes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme our faith in thy promiſes temporall and ſpirituall; teach vs to loue thee feruently, to deſpiſe riches, pleaſures, pride, and all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vanities. Teach vs obedience to our ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, and loue to all men, euen to our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, much more to all thy deare children.</p>
               <p>Preſerue vs and euerie one of vs this day and euery <note place="margin">Heere let thoſe ſinnes be named which are moſt practiſed in the family.</note> day from ſwearing, curſing, lying, from reproaching and ſlaundering, from deceit and oppreſſion, and all other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences againſt thy Maieſty, or againſt our Neighbour, from idleneſſe, gluttony, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, intemperance; from chambering and wantonneſſe, from ſtrife and enuie, from all ſinfull words or deeds, from all vnlawfull attempts or purpoſes. O pardon all our ſins paſt, aſſure our ſoules of this forgiueneſſe; giue vs grace to hate all manner of ſinnes in others, and ſpecially in our ſelues, to be watchfull ouer our waies, to be conſtant in all good purpoſes.</p>
               <p>O Lord, bleſſe and defend thy vniuerſall Church, our Soueraigne King, the Queene,
<pb facs="tcp:19946:34"/> and all the Royall progeny, the Nobles and Magiſtrates, the Biſhops and Miniſters. O be fauorable and gracious to al that are neere and deare to vs, direct and proſper euery one of vs in all our intended labours and buſineſſes. For theſe and all good things needfull for vs, and for all thy children, we pray as our deare Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our hath taught vs;</p>
               <q>Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</q>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A ſhort Euening Prayer.</head>
               <p>MOſt gracious God, and mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we preſent our ſelues before thy glorious Maieſty, in the name and media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Ieſus Chriſt, moſt humbly beſeeching thee for his ſake, to forgiue all the ſinnes of this day, our worldly affections, our inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and carking cares and griefes, our greedy deſire after earthly things, our ouer-valuing of theſe earthly vanities, and our neglect of heauenly things: O pardon all our vaine, vnprofitable, and vnſauoury talke, all omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of good duties, to thee or to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, all our corruptions and defects, in thoſe which we haue taken in hand.</p>
               <p>Forgiue all the ſinfull acts of this day, and
<pb facs="tcp:19946:35"/> of our whole life: Grant that wee may ſearch out our ſinnes diligently, and diſcouer them, and ſtedfaſtly reſolue to reforme them without delay, and enable vs by thy Spirit to performe what wee intend, that we may be conſtant in all good purpoſes and enterpriſes.</p>
               <p>Grant that euery day wee may crucifie the old man, that our naturall pride, malice, enuie, ſtrife, may die in vs; that couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, infidelity, truſt in riches, or howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer in the arme of fleſh; that wanton luſts and deſires may be mortified in vs, that idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and voluptuous liuing may be hatefull to vs. Grant that wee may practiſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vertues, that humility before thee and before men, that charity in forgiuing wrongs in word or deed, and in helping and relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the wants of our neighbours, may abound in vs, that faith and loue, that tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and ſobriety, may ſhine bright in vs, that we may be iuſt and faithfull in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts and dealings with all men. Quicken vs euer to all religious duties, to praier and thankſgiuing, let vs aboue all things delight in the conſtant reading, hearing, and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy Word, aſſure vs of the pardon of our ſinnes, of thy loue and fauour, and of our euerlaſting ſaluation.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:35"/>
               <p> Let vs euery day thinke on death, on the reſurrection, and the laſt Iudgement, and that not with horror and griefe, but with great ioy and comfort: Let vs vnfainedly deſire, and euery day prepare our ſelues to be with Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Make vs heartily thankefull for all thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, for publike and priuate benefits, ſo many and ſo great, for our food and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, our peace and ſafety, and ſpecially for our election, redemption, and effectuall vocation.</p>
               <p>Bleſſe, O LORD, thy vniuerſall Church, comfort thy ſeruants that are pinched with want, thoſe that are afflicted with warre, perſecutions, or with inward tentations, or whatſoeuer tribulations.</p>
               <p>Preſerue and direct our ſoueraigne King, bleſſe the Queene, and all the Royall Iſſue, the Nobles and Magiſtrates, the Biſhops and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and the reſt of thy people. Bleſſe and preſerue this family, giue vs quiet reſt and ſleepe, raiſe vs vp in due time, to doe thee ſeruice in our ſeuerall places.</p>
               <p>For theſe and all good things, we pray as thy Sonne our Sauiour hath taught vs,</p>
               <q>Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</q>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:36"/>
               <head>A Prayer for a young Scholler, or any of the younger ſort, both Morning and Euening.</head>
               <p>MOſt gracious God and louing Father, I giue thee moſt humble and hearty thankes for all thy mercies; for chooſing me to ſaluation, and redeeming me with the precious bloud of Chriſt my Sauiour, for calling mee to this great honour, to be one of the number of thy children, by working in my heart true faith, and hatred of all ſinne, by thy holy Word both read and preached, and by thy bleſſed Spirit. And I praiſe thy holy Name for my health, for my food and raiment, for good nurture, and godly educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for my preſeruation this
<list>
                     <item>night</item>
                     <item>day</item>
                  </list> paſt, and at all times.</p>
               <p>O Lord continue thy fauour towards me, teach me to know thee, to loue and feare thee, to keepe all thy Commandements. Let not the corruption of my nature, nor the craft of Satan, nor euill company, nor any worldly vanity, withdraw me from thee. Suffer me not to ſlide from thee into any falſe
<pb facs="tcp:19946:36"/> beleefe, or an vngodly life, but inſtruct mee in all truth and godlineſſe, in all ſobriety and righteouſneſſe. O Lord, forgiue me all my ſinnes, teach me to diſcerne them, to hate and forſake them: grant that I may beſtow vpon thee all the daies of my youth, and ſo continue thy faithfull ſeruant to my liues end.</p>
               <p>O Lord preſerue thy Church, our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne King, the Queene, and all the Royall Iſſue, the Magiſtrates, and Miniſters of thy Word, and all thy people. Bleſſe my deare Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, brethren, ſiſters, &amp; other friends; bleſſe this whole family; giue me health, defend me from idleneſſe,
<list>
                     <item>learning,</item>
                     <item>buſineſſe,</item>
                  </list> defend mee in proſper my ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, this
<list>
                     <item>night</item>
                     <item>day</item>
                  </list> and euermore. Amen.</p>
               <q>Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c,</q>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:37"/>
               <head>Another Morning Prayer for a young Scholler.</head>
               <p>O Lord, my God and louing Father, I giue thee humble thanks for all thy benefits, for my ſleep &amp; ſafety this night, for my food and apparel, for religious education, and for the precious treaſure of thy moſt holy word. Lord bleſſe me this day and euer, giue me health: Keepe me from ſin, proſper my learning. Lord be mercifull to my parents: grant I may honor them according to thy Commandement, that by my weldoing I may be a comfort vnto them: defend them and me, and al this family, and al the reſt of thy people in ſoule and body this day and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:19946:37"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
